Guide to the Oregon Hops and Brewing Archives Oral History Collection 2014-2017
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections and Archives Research Center
- Interviews, 2017; Series 4
  - Larsen, Lee, February 20, 2017
    Lee Larsen is one of the founders of 2 Towns Ciderhouse in Corvallis, Oregon. In this interview, he talks about growing up in Corvallis and experiences living in Barcelona, Spain during high school. Specifically, Larsen reflects on the cultural differences around the drinking and production of alcohol in Spain and the U.S., as well as his early exposure to the astringent Basque ciders he encountered. Larsen also talks about his time at OSU studying Finance (BS 2008) and his early interest in home brewing. Larsen ends the interview talking about establishing 2 Towns with Aaron Sarnoff-Wood in 2010, the addition of Dave Takush in 2011, and the company culture. This interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton at 2 Towns Ciderhouse on February 20, 2017.
  - Takush, Dave, February 20, 2017
    Dave Takush is the head cider maker at 2 Towns Ciderhouse in Corvallis, Oregon. In his interview, Takush talks about growing up in Corvallis, his undergraduate and graduate studies in Fermentation Science and Oenology at OSU (BS 2007, MS 2009), and his work as a winemaker in Eugene. Takush also shares information about New World (modern) apple and Traditional (heritage) apples, specifically as it relates to their commitment as a business to bring back the traditional cider style, concerns over cider apple supply, experiences finding and grafting new varieties of apple trees, opportunities to work with both local orchardists and the local community, and the importance of agricultural history. Takush also talks about the early company history, working with Lee Larsen and Aaron Sarnoff-Wood, and the company culture. This interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton at 2 Towns Ciderhouse on February 20, 2017.
  - Kirk, Nathan, February 21, 2017
    Dr. Nathan Kirk is a teaches in OSU's Department of Integrative Biology, specializing in Marine Ecology. In this interview, Dr. Kirk talks about growing up in New York state, his early research interests and education, his experiences in his graduate program at State University of New York at Buffalo and doctoral program at Auburn University (Alabama). He also talks about his experiences as a home brewer, specifically as it related to the culture in Alabama and his own brewing practices. This interview was conducted by Gillian Bergmann and Tiah Edmunson-Morton in Cordley Hall on OSU's campus on February 21, 2017.
  - Stevens, Hilda, February 22, 2017
    Hilda Stevens owns Bazi Bierbrasserie, a Belgian-style beer taproom and soccer bar in SE Portland. In her interview, Stevens talks about immigrating from Guatemala when she was 8 years old, living and going to school in The Woodlands (a community north of Houston, Texas), attending St Mary's University in San Antonio, her early work with business and marketing companies, experiences traveling through the US and internationally, and her work establishing Bazi. This interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton at Bazi Bierbrasserie in Portland Oregon on February 22, 2017.
  - Sarnoff-Wood, Aaron, February 24, 2017
    Aaron Sarnoff-Wood is one of the co-founders of 2 Towns Ciderhouse in Corvallis, Oregon. In this interview, Sarnoff-Wood talks about growing up in Corvallis, his early interest in art and graphic design, attending the University of Oregon, work in the graphic design industry, and the decision to open a cider-making company with Lee Larsen. Sarnoff-Wood also reflects on the evolution and growth of the cider industry, as well as how the company has changed with its increase in size. This interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton at 2 Towns Ciderhouse in Corvallis, Oregon on February 24, 2017.
  - Clawson, Jeffrey, February 27, 2017
    Jeff Clawson has worked for the Department of Food Science and Technology as the research brewery and food processing manager since 1993. In his interview, Clawson talks about growing up in Davis, California, where his father was a University of California Extension Agent and his mom worked as a department admin assistant. He also shares his early memories of Davis, thoughts on campus and city culture, and his decision to move to Oregon to attend Eastern Oregon College (now Eastern Oregon University) in LaGrande, where he studied Agribusiness. It was in college that Clawson took a class in brewing, which became a personal hobby and ultimately led to a career. He talks about transferring to OSU to finish his BS, adding a food science minor and working with Mina McDaniel on sensory analysis; about working for NORPAC Foods in Stayton after graduation; about returning to OSU for graduate school in 1991 to study Rangeland Resources and Water Quality; and finally about returning to the food sciences in 1993. Clawson talks about the gift from James Bernau that facilitated building the pilot research brewery and establishing the Nor'Wester endowed professorship, the evolution of the program, and the future of brewing education at OSU. This interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton at the Valley Library in Corvallis, Oregon on February 27, 2017.
  - Tobin, Jeff, Kathy, and Gillian, February 28, 2017
    Jeff, Kathy and Gillian Tobin are the owners of Mazama Brewing Company, which was founded in Corvallis, Oregon in 2012. In this interview, Jeff Tobin discusses his childhood in Michigan, being interested in both science and music at school, and how those interests lead him to studying electronic engineering at Michigan Technical University. He also discusses how he and his wife Kathy were introduced to home brewing by peers at the university, and how they developed their skills in German styles. Jeff then recounts his career path from International Business Machines (IBM) in Vermont to Hewlett Packard (HP) in Colorado and Corvallis, Oregon, noting the birth of his children, Gillian and Riley, during that time. Kathy then joins the interview and she, along with Gillian and Jeff, discuss how they decided to open Mazama brewing, the importance of community involvement and the overlap between their relationships as family and business partners. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton at the Mazama Brewing taproom in Corvallis, Oregon.
  - Loranz, Nick, March 2, 2017
    Nick Lorenz is one of the founders and owners of Nectar Creek Mead, which opened up in October of 2012. In this interview, Lorenz discusses growing up with his brother Phillip in Corvallis, their early involvement in farming and value-added agriculture, and his individual interests in soccer and pottery. He then discusses how he decided to go to the University of Vermont studying ecological agriculture, his journey towards giving up soccer and the summer jobs he held as a raft guide and orchard staff member. In addition to this, Lorenz elaborates on his brother’s college education in apiculture/fermentation science and work in commercial beekeeping, and how those experiences lead to the opening of the meadery after years of planning to run a business together. Lorenz then details the growth Nectar Creek has experienced since starting, and how he incorporates his value of personal connection into their involvement in the community and their employment model. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton at the Nectar Creek Meadery in Corvallis, Oregon.
  - McKay, Mark, March 8, 2017
    Mark McKay is a sixth generation hop grower in St. Paul, Oregon. In his interview, McKay talks about his family history, growing up on the farm, crops they have grown, why his dad got out of the hops business, and things he learned from his father and the community. He also talks about establishing a hop farm in Independence in the 1990s with his brother Dean, industry labor practices and regulations, the challenges of an evolving industry, agro-tourism, the impact of technology on farming, as well as his thoughts on the future of farming and his hopes for his children’s involvement in the industry. This interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton at McKay's house in St. Paul, Oregon on March 8, 2017. Also present was McKay's daughter, Michelle.
  - Coleman, Bill, March 8, 2017
    Bill Coleman is part of a large multigenerational hop growing family, primarily based in St. Paul and Mt. Angel. In his interview Coleman talks about his family’s history with hops in the Willamette Valley, growing up in a farming family, jobs he did as a child and adult, and the strong work ethic and values that were part of his upbringing. He also talks about the rapid expansion of farm land his family experienced in the 1950s through 1970s, the locations of the farms throughout the counties of the Valley, business relationships with other farming families and the monks at Mt. Angel Abbey, labor history and changes over time, and technologies he developed to improve efficiencies. He addresses the roles of different family members in current company structure, how to hand down knowledge through generations, and how they value communication. He shares his thoughts on his own travels and the value he places on meeting new people and appreciating the place he is from. This interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton at Bill Coleman's sister's house in Mt. Angel, Oregon on March 8, 2017. Also present was Coleman's sister Jane Wavra and great niece Michelle McKay.
  - Morrison, Lisa, March 15, 2017
    Lisa Morrison is the majority owner at Belmont Station in Portland. In her interview, Morrison talks about growing up in Oklahoma, moving to Colorado for high school, and college experiences at Colorado State University. It was at CSU that her interest in imported and local microbrews was sparked. After graduating with a degree in Technical Journalism, Morrison was a television news reporter and anchor, a career she continued after moving to Portland in 1989. In addition to exploring the rapidly expanding beer culture in Portland, she began home brewing with her husband and soon joined the Oregon Brew Crew. Soon this personal interest or avocation turned into a career when she started to write about beer for local and national publications, and then later a radio show where she interviewed people from all aspects of the brewing community. Morrison talks about her process for identifying and chronicling beer culture, experiences as a woman in the journalism and brewing industries, beer education/appreciation classes she taught (including Sud Sisters, Barleys Angels), experiences mentoring and encouraging exploration of styles, and her impact on the industry, as well as her work establishing well-known festivals like PDX Beer Week, Craft Beer Month, and Fred Fest. The interview was conducted on March 15, 2017 by Tiah Edmunson-Morton at Belmont Station in Portland, Oregon.
  - Nance, Gary, March 17, 2017
    Gary Nance is the brewer at the McMenamins on Monroe in Corvallis, Oregon. Nance started brewing professionally in 1995, working as the assistant brewer at Spencer's Restaurant and Brewhouse in Springfield, Oregon, where he helped develop Oregon's first certified organic ale in 1998. After Spencer's closed, he had short stints working at West Bros. and Steelhead before taking a job at the McMenamins Thompson Brewery and Public House in Salem in August 2002. Nance moved to the new Monroe Street facility when it opened in 2006. In his interview, Nance talks about growing up in Oklahoma, moving to the West Coast, living in Eugene, his growing interest in brewing, and his experiences at several different breweries in different cities. He also talks about McMenamins culture and balancing brewing experimentation with the expected standardization in a company. The interview was conducted on March 17, 2017 by Tiah Edmunson-Morton in the McMenamins Monroe brewery in Corvallis, Oregon.
  - Clack, Brad, March 22, 2017
    Brad Clack is a retired hop buyer for SS Steiner (now Hopsteiner). In his interview, Clack talks about his family's farm work on the Oregon coast, growing up in Salem, Oregon, and changes in the hop industry since he started in 1978. Clack also talks about the importance of the relationships in the industry and challenges for handing down knowledge, as well as his experiences managing the hop marketing orders. This interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on March 22, 2017 at the Hopsteiner offices in Brookes, Oregon. Also present was Michelle McKay.
  - Perkins, Sybil, March 27, 2017
    Sybil Perkins is the brand director and a board member for the Pink Boots Society. In her interview, Perkins talks about growing up in the Eugene/Springfield area, her interest and passion for arts and music, her early and evolving work as an activist, her experiences living in Philadelphia and New York City, and her return to the west coast to the greater Seattle area. She talks specifically about her work doing graphic design and marketing work with the brewing industry, her views on gender and inclusion, and how the mission and outreach of the Pink Boots Society has expanded over the past few years. This interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on March 27, 2017 at Perkins' home in Snohomish, Washington.
  - Schumacher, Robyn, March 27, 2017
    Robyn Schumacher is a brewer at Stoup Brewing in Seattle's Ballard district. In her interview, Schumacher talks about growing up in Spokane, her early interest in sports and science, and about choosing to go to Carroll College to study biology in Helena, Montana. Schumacher also discusses her early career as a high school teacher and factors that influenced her decision to shift to jobs in the restaurant and brewing industries. She talks specifically about learning to home brew, studying for the cicerone exam (she was the first woman in Washington to be certified), exploring the brewing community, and the story of her co-ownership of Stoup. This interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on March 27, 2017 at Stoup Brewing in Seattle, Washington.
  - Woodall, Ralph, March 28, 2017
    Ralph Woodall works in sales for Yakima-Chief Hopunion, a company he has been with since the mid-1980s. In his interview, Woodall talks about his family history in the Yakima Valley, his work in the hop industry, his present role in the larger YCH company, and the changes in the Master Brewers Association of America with the decrease in large regional breweries and the emergence of the craft industry. Woodall also shows a number of pictures from festivals, trade shows, and other events he took over the years. Of special note are the pictures of NW brewers. This interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on March 28, 2017 at Yakima-Chief Hopunion in Yakima, Washington.
  - Carpenter, Tom, March 28, 2017
    Tom Carpenter is a 4th generation hop grower based in Granger, Washington. In his interview, Carpenter talks about the history of hops in the Yakima Valley, his families' important role in the grower cooperative that eventually became Yakima Chief, the role of family in their business, and the role of Native Americans in the hops industry. This interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on March 28, 2017 at Carpenter Ranch in Granger, Washington.
  - Coleman, John, April 19, 2017
    ​John Coleman is a hop grower based in St. Paul, Oregon. He manages the hops and perennial crops for Coleman Ag, a large family run company. In his interview Coleman talks about growing up in St. Paul, working on the farm, and attending OSU in the 1980s. He also talks extensively about the family business, including their partnership with Rogue Ales and the farm in Independence, potential collaboration with the brewery at the Abbey in Mount Angel, and ways he thinks the company can continue to grow or change to meet new needs. The interview was conducted by Michelle McKay in St. Paul, Oregon on April 19, 2017. Also present was Tiah Edmunson-Morton.
  - Wills, Dave, April 24, 2017
    Dave Wills is the owner of Freshops, Oregon Trail Brewery, and Dave's Christmas Trees. In his interview, Wills talks about growing up in Southern California, moving to Oregon to attend OSU, and how his early interest in home brewing was sparked by a trip through Europe. He details the early home brewing community in Corvallis, establishing Fresh Hops to supply the home brewing community, and the evolution of Oregon Trail Brewing, which opened in October 1987. Wills also discusses changes he's seen in the local and state brewing industry, the hops supply business, and the consumers. This interview was conducted by Michelle McKay and Tiah Edmunson-Morton on April 24, 2017 at Oregon Trail Brewery in Corvallis Oregon.
  - Conn, Denny, May 1, 2017
    Denny Conn is a home brewer, author, and podcaster. In his interview, Conn talks about his time playing and touring with rock bands, his work as an audio engineer, and how he became involved with home brewing. Conn is known for his experimental brewing techniques, and he details the evolution of his own brewing, how challenging traditional method or ingredients can advance a home brewers, his partnership with Drew Beechum in writing and podcasting, and the ways he's seen home brewing change over time. This interview was conducted on May 1, 2017 at the Valley Library in Corvallis, Oregon.
  - Dettwyler, William, May 17, 2017
    William Dettwyler grew up on a hop farm in Silverton, Oregon. In his interview he talks extensively about his family farm, processing facilities, and operations in the 1930s through the 1950s. This interview was conducted by Michelle McKay and Tiah Edmunson-Morton on May 17, 2017 in the Valley Library in Corvallis, Oregon.
  - Just, Jessica, May 25, 2017
    Jessica Just is the Director of Technical Services for Brew Dr. Kombucha in Portland, Oregon. Just was one of the first three graduates, and first female, from the OSU Fermentation Science program in the Food Science Department, which was established in 1995. In her interview Just discusses growing up in Portland, early home brewing experiences, her undergraduate and graduate work at OSU in the 1990s, work with the wine industry in California, and time in London and work with the local chapter of the Campaign for Real Ale. She also talks about moving back to Corvallis to take a job as an academic advisor and instructor for the Fermentation Science program, and her new job at Brew Dr. Kombucha. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on May 25, 2017 at the Valley Library in Corvallis, Oregon.
  - Rea, Joel, June 8, 2017
    Joel Rea is the owner of Corvallis Brewing Supply. In his interview Rea talks about his early life in Kirkland, Washington; moving to Albany, Oregon in elementary school; his college work in environmental studies and the fine arts, and his decision to change careers to open a home brew shop. He also discusses his experiments with fermentation, brewers he's worked with and mentored, challenges to operate a supply shop in the Internet age, and how he's seen consumers evolve since the shop opened in 1997. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on June 8, 2017 at Corvallis Brewing Supply in downtown Corvallis.
  - Fish, Gary, June 12, 2017
    Gary Fish is the founder and board president of Deschutes Brewery. In his interview, Fish talks about growing up in California, his early career in the restaurant industries in Utah, and the establishment of the brewery in Bend. He also discusses the evolution of the city of Bend, as well how the company has grown and expanded. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on June 12, 2017 in Bend, Oregon.
  - Vega, Veronica, June 12, 2017
    Veronica Vega is a Brewmaster at Deschutes Brewery, focusing on research and development. In her interview, Vega talks about growing up in Southern California, her college time at Humboldt State University studying Botany, her brief stint in the forest service, and her move to Bend. Vega also discusses how her work has changed at the company, including her movement up the company, starting as a tour guide and moving up to one of the top brewer position. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on June 12, 2017 in Bend, Oregon.
  - Ockert, Karl, June 13, 2017
    Karl Ockert is the Director of Brewery Operations at Deschutes Brewery. In his interview, Ockert talks about his childhood adventures, including home brewing with his mom, as well as his education at Humboldt State University and UC Davis, his role as the first brewer at BridgePort Brewing in Portland from 1984 to 1990, his time at Anheuser Busch in Newark, his return to BridgePort in 1996, his work at the Master Brewers Association of America as the Technical Director and as a professional brewing consultant, and his position at Deschutes Brewery. Ockert also talks about how he has seen the industry change and concerns he has about acquisitions of microbreweries by macro breweries. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on June 13, 2017 in Bend, Oregon.